Finding Aid for Delta Upsilon Fraternity, University of Michigan Chapter records, 1876-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Delta Upsilon Fraternity, University of Michigan Chapter records 1876-1991
Delta Upsilon Fraternity. University of Michigan Chapter.
861091 Bimu F47 2
University of Michigan chapter of a fraternal organization with an academic orientation. Constitution, minute books, treasurer's books, pledge class yearbooks, and visual materials.
7 linear feet
16 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record came from the fraternity (donor no. 1634 ) in periodic accessions beginning in March 1942.
Further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Delta Upsilon was established as a non-secret fraternal organization with an academic orientation. Prominent in the early literature of the society was the motto, "Scholarship must be first for the conscientious student." The University of Michigan chapter of Delta Upsilon was founded in 1876.
In the absence of a corporate facility, fraternal business was originally conducted in a hall above Schuh's Hardware Store on Main Street. The activities of Delta Upsilon during the first quarter century of its incarnation on the University of Michigan campus were predominantly literary and theatrical. The annual commemoration of the chapter's founding, falling on Shakespeare's birthday, was commemorated by the production of a Shakespearian drama. Delta Upsilon was also instrumental in securing the dissolution of the "Palladium", a consortium of secret fraternal organizations that had monopolized student positions of influence at the University of Michigan.
In 1902 Delta Upsilon purchased two lots on the north side of Hill street, east of Forest Avenue with the intention of building a fraternal housing facility. This was to be the first such structure built at the University of Michigan. Construction funds were raised through the sale of mortgage bonds and additional funds were obtained by selling several rental properties belonging to the fraternity. Construction of the house was begun in 1903 at a cost of $16,425.
The advent of World War II witnessed an acute shortage of housing at the university. The members of Delta Upsilon volunteered to remove to a boarding house, making the chapter house available as an army barracks. Upon returning to 1331 Hill street at the conclusion of the war, it was determined that extensive remodeling and expansion of the house was required. Accommodations were expanded through the construction of an annex to the main facility.
Limits on available space continued to pose problems leading to a proposal for relocation to the University's North Campus. Plans for a "frat row" on North campus did not materialize and in 1968 the annex was demolished to make way for a large addition to the chapter house. An alumni fund drive provided resources for the addition.
A concern with the strict regulation of social interaction between the sexes and the prevalence of alcohol use among students led to periodic investigations of Greek life by the university administration in the middle decades of the twentieth century. Delta Upsilon, in conjunction with three other fraternities, was suspended for a semester in 1950 for sponsoring a party at which the use of alcohol was accompanied by the conspicuous absence of non-student chaperones. The fraternity was readmitted at the conclusion of the probationary period without incident.
Delta Upsilon continues to play a prominent role in the social life of the University of Michigan. The original chapter house and the 1968 addition currently meet the housing requirements of the members of Delta Upsilon.
The records of Delta Upsilon have been divided into three series: Organizational Materials, Scrapbooks, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Delta Upsilon Fraternity. University of Michigan Chapter.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Clubhouses.; Delta Upsilon Fraternity. University of Michigan Chapter.; Fraternities and sororities.; Interiors--Clubhouses.; University of Michigan--Students--1871-1880.; University of Michigan--Students--1881-1890.; University of Michigan--Students--1901-1910.; University of Michigan--Students--1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Students--1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--1931-1940.; University of Michigan--Students--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Students--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Students--1981-1990.
Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Photographs.; Songbooks.
- Organizational Materials
  The Organizational Materials series, 1876-1969, is predominantly composed of minutes from directors' meetings and chapter meetings, which include information on legal and financial matters as well as social events. Also included are a copy of the fraternity's original constitution and Treasurer's books, 1894-1915. Treasurer's books contain detailed information on expenditures and payment of membership dues.
  - Constitution, attendance record and speeches 1876-1884 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - Directors' meetings 1884-1923 (Box 1)
    - Chapter meetings
      - 1876-1883 (Box 1)
      - 1884-1896 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1902 (Box 1)
      - 1902-1906 (Box 1)
      - 1908-1915 (Box 1)
      - 1915-1919 (Box 1)
      - 1919-1929 1946-1947 (Box 1)
      - 1930-1932 (Box 2)
      - 1932-1935 (Box 2)
  - Songbook, 1918 (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's book
    - 1894-1900 (Box 2)
    - 1904-1913 (Box 2)
    - 1914-1915 (Box 2)
  - House notes 1890-1898, 3 volumes (Box 2)
    (includes construction data and expenses)
  - Miscellanea 1884-1953 (Box 2)
  - Reminiscences of fraternity life before and after WWII by William Sterling Maxwell 1988 (Box 2)
  - Fund Drive 1968-1969 (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series spans the years 1901-1932 (volumes referred to as pledge class yearbooks) and 1946-1991. The scrapbooks contain photographs of fraternity members, social events, and interior and exterior views of the fraternity house. Newspaper clippings, reminiscences, and humorous anecdotes are also evident.
  - Pledge class yearbooks 1901-1932, 19 volumes (Box 3)
    The pledge class yearbooks include photos of members, both alone and as part of group activities, photos of fraternity house (exterior and interior), and occasional drawings illustrating college life.
  - 1946-1947 (Box 4)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 4)
  - Fall 1948 (Box 4)
  - 1948/1949 (Volume 1)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 4)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 4)
  - Fall 1952 (Box 4)
  - Spring 1953 (Volume 2)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 4)
  - Fall 1954 (Volume 16)
  - Fall 1955 (Box 4)
  - Fall 1955 (Volume 3)
  - Fall 1956 (Volume 4)
  - Spring 1957 (Volume 5)
  - Fall 1957 (Box 5)
  - Spring 1958, 2 volumes (Box 5)
  - Fall 1959 (Volume 6)
  - 1959/1960 (Volume 7)
  - Fall 1960 (Volume 8)
  - Spring 1961 (Volume 9)
  - Spring 1961 (Volume 10)
  - Spring 1962 (Box 5)
  - Fall 1962 (Volume 11)
  - Spring 1963 (Box 5)
  - Fall 1963 (Box 5)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 5)
  - Spring 1964 (Volume 12)
  - Fall 1964 (Box 5)
  - Spring 1966 (Box 5)
  - Fall 1982 (Box 5)
  - Fall 1983 (Box 6)
  - Fall 1984 (Box 6)
  - Spring 1985 (Volume 13)
  - Fall 1985 (Box 6)
  - Spring 1986 (Box 6)
  - Fall 1986 (Volume 14)
  - Spring 1987 (Box 6)
  - Fall 1987 (Box 6)
  - Spring 1988 (Volume 15)
  - Spring 1989 (Box 7)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 7)
- Photographs
  - Album 1879-1890: portraits of members (Box 7)